The first edition
第一版
This is the second edition
这是第二版
Speaking of the first edition
在第一版来讲的话
It’s relatively thinner
他那个书啊比较薄
But how do we describe the content inside?
但是里边的内容呢怎么说呢
Actually, this is the only one that hasn't been revised.
其实这个仅此一本还没有修改过的
Most of the original manuscripts,
大多数的原稿
Of course,
当然来讲
This can't be sold outside.
那这个不能不能不能在外边卖啊
The second one here is already,
这第二本里头已经是啊
Look, the cover is in excellent condition,
你看这封封的非常好
And it's very thick and sturdy,
然后非常的厚实
And it has a great feel to it.
然后他这个手感非常好
And then there's the special edition with the gold edges.
然后还有专门的那个就是那个金边版
That one is a limited release.
那个是特殊发行的
Only about
就只有啊
I remember it should be around 1,000 copies.
大概我记得应该是1000册吧
So everyone, come to Shandong Book City on the 19th.
然后呢呃大家19号到这个山东书城来讲
I'll be there with my signed editions.
有我的亲签版啊
The signed editions are also available online,
亲签版在网上也能买到
but at the event, it’s guaranteed
但是现场是百分之百
that you’ll get a signed copy.
你会得到亲签版
I think he's about to exhaust himself with all the signing.
我觉得签的他自己都快累死了啊
Yeah, it's the first book of the 'Life Hacks for B' series.
就是啊B坑人生大攻略的第一本书啊
I have three books.
我三本书啊
The third one hasn't even started yet.
第三本还没开始动笔
The second one is already finalized. The first one has already been published. Everyone is welcome to buy them. They are very suitable. You can start watching in the Douyin Live from April 19th. You can buy it directly in Bilibili's live room.
第二本已经定稿了 第一本这已经是出版了啊 这个欢迎大家来购买啊 这个非常合适 你们在4月19号开始就可以在抖音直播间 可以在B站的直播间啊
You can buy it directly.
可以直接买到啊
They are Douyin Store and this one.
分别是抖店和这个啊
This is Taobao.
这个这个这个这个这个啊淘宝啊
The book won't be available in electronic format for a while.
呃这个书呢不会暂时不会那么快出电子版啊
I hope everyone allows me to sell it for a while.
大家允许我卖一段时间啊
We'll talk about it after some time.
过一段时间说啊
I am a student.
我是学生
It's not expensive.
那个我那个那什么不贵
It's just a few dozen bucks
就几十块钱啊
the cost of a meal
吃顿饭的
what you'd spend on takeout
吃顿外卖的钱
and it will probably take about a year before it's available
然后呢就是呃大概得过一年才能上架
things like WeChat Reading
什么微信读书之类的
my editor summarized this for me
呃我的编辑给我总结了这个啊
how should I put it
我的这个这个这个这个这个怎么说呢
uh
这个这个这个这个这个这个呃
what my book is mainly about
我的书主要写的是什么
Since I've been writing for quite a while
因为写的时间够长了
I'm a bit forgetful now
我也现在有点忘了
Let me summarize for everyone
给大家总结一下呃
Rong Zhen's grand life strategy for young friends Break through with courage and avoid pitfalls with wisdom Don't let others' expectations become your chains Time will unlock confusion Wisdom can help you avoid pitfalls and provide a safety net Instead of worrying about the future Focus on the present instead.
荣振献给广大青年朋友的人生大攻略 破局靠胆识避坑平智慧 别让别人的期待成为你的枷锁 时间会解锁困惑 智慧能够避坑托底 与其焦虑未来 不如专注当下
What once made you stumble will eventually become the path beneath your feet.
那些曾经让你跌倒的终会成为脚下的路
In families, understanding each other is more important than confrontation.
家庭学会理解比对抗更重要啊
Actually, in many cases,
其实很多的时候来讲
when we talk about life,
我们说人生在世呢
drawing from my personal experience,
很多的时候以我个人为经验吧
back when I was in my twenties,
就是我在20多岁
the mistakes I made in my thirties,
30多岁的时候犯过的错误呢
are pretty much all included here.
好基本上来讲都写进去了
When it comes to emotions,
不管是情感上的
social aspects,
社会上的
economic factors,
经济上的
career paths,
事业上的
and choices in education,
学业的选择上面来讲
they're all covered.
基本都在里边
I think most things,
其实我觉得大部分东西呢
can be considered part of general education,
大家呢可以说是通识的教育
but often, you know what something is without understanding why it is that way.
其实很多东西你是知其然不知其所以然啊
Some things, when broken down,
有些东西掰开了
when thoroughly examined,
揉碎了以后
they might reveal a deeper meaning.
他可能有一层更深层的意思
Actually, many of life's pitfalls are hard to escape once you fall into them.
其实人生当中很多的坑呢进去了是出不来的啊
But, to put it another way, it's about a shift in consciousness.
但是来讲我们说它是一种意识的改变啊
If you had met me earlier,
我就是说如果你要是早一点认识我
or watched my videos a few years ago, your entire perception of life might have been different. I hope everyone's journey through life is smooth and clear. Smooth sailing You don’t have to walk as cautiously as I did
或者早几年看我的视频 可能你人生的整个的感觉是不一样的 希望大家的人生路都是坦荡的啊 坦途啊 不用像我说的这个呃轻一脚浅一脚啊
Feeling your way across the river by touching the stones
摸着河头石头过河啊
It’s hard to put into words
深意怎么说呢
It’s entirely
就是完完全全
Back then, I wished that my future self, 20 years from now
我那时候希望如果哈20年以后的我
Could guide me through my confusion
能够为我当时呢给我指点迷津
Give me a book like this
给我这么一本书啊
I think it would be a really great thing
我也觉得其实是非常好的事情啊
There's no need to say anything more.
大家呢也不用说啊
Bro Rong,
荣哥
What's the difference between this video and the book?
你这个这个这个视频跟这个书有什么不一样
Let me tell you, the content of the book is more classical.
我跟你讲书的内容更加文言一些
More formal, actually.
更加书面化一些
But it's still very enjoyable to read.
其实你读起来还是很舒服的
And you can give the book as a gift to your friends.
而且书你可以送朋友
You can even use it to enlighten your parents.
还可以给你爸妈洗脑
This is really important.
这个东西很重要啊
When it comes to videos
视频来讲的话
Speaking of these over a thousand videos
我这个1000多个视频来讲
After everyone has finished watching them all
大家全看完了以后
The focus is on these three books of mine
集中是在我这三本书上
Actually, it's pretty good
其实挺好啊
There's quite a bit of chatter in my videos
我视频里边儿废话比较多啊
The content in the books is more concise
书里边比较精炼一点啊
So it's actually great to buy them and keep as favorites
所以其实买来收藏啊
They are really excellent
非常好啊
Bro Long will personally sign ten sentences for you.
龙哥会十句话给你亲签的
Now, let's talk about the topic of this episode.
然后我们讲一讲这期的主题
Let's dive into the topic of this episode.
我们就讲这期的主题呢
Many people say that what you're talking about is Western philosophy. Actually, it's not Western philosophy. A lot of what I talk about is the philosophy of Laozi and Zhuangzi. The ideas of Wang Yangming as well. First, let's talk about Zhuangzi.
其实很多人在说你讲的是西方的哲学 其实不是西方的哲学 我讲的好多都是老庄的思想啊 王阳明的思想 咱们说首先就是说庄子
He talked about this person.
他说这个人啊
So, what exactly can one do to avoid depression?
其实人到底怎么样做才能避免这个抑郁呢
Why do so many people suffer from depression?
为什么很多人抑郁呢
Zhuangzi didn’t specify.
庄子呢没说啊
He didn’t go into detail about how to avoid it.
具体说怎么样才能避免
You might first feel very, very down.
你先身体感觉很很抑郁啊
Or you might find yourself trapped in a state of anxiety.
或者是陷入一种焦虑情绪当中
He gave an example.
他举了个例子
He mentioned the story of Bo Le recognizing a fine horse.
他就说这伯乐识马啊
He talked about how a horse meets its true connoisseur.
说这个马遇到伯乐
Is it a good thing or a bad thing?
到底是件好事还是件不好的事情
A wise judge recognizes you as a thousand-mile horse.
伯乐识你为千里马
But what is the price you have to pay to become a thousand-mile horse?
但是你成为千里马的代价是什么呢
You need to be bridled.
需要给你上嚼子啊
Put on this saddle.
套这个马鞍
Shoe the horse.
钉马掌
Burn off the mixed hairs.
烧杂毛
And even give you a good fanning.
还要扇了你啊
In many cases, speaking of which,
很多的时候来讲的话
A form of social persuasion
人对社会化的一种规劝
Or the education system molds you into an excellent worker
或者说教育系统给你设定成一个优秀的打工人
Society turns you into a useful person
社会让你变成了有用的人
But this usefulness is from society's perspective, this excellence This is what society values It's specific to certain contexts But what about you, from the perspective of Laozi and Zhuangzi's philosophy From the perspective of Daoist philosophy
但是这种有用是对社会来讲的这种呀优秀啊 这种人才是对啊 特定的对象而说的 但是你自己呢作为老庄哲学 作为这个道家的哲学
Valuing tranquility and non-action, becoming one with nature
对清静无为啊成为自然的状态啊
So, a lot of the time, it's about showing respect to heaven and earth.
所以说这个很多的时候都是说啊敬天地啊
First, how do we talk about the unity of heaven and humanity?
先以天地怎么说天人合一
This is the realm that Taoism strives to achieve.
这是道家追求的境界啊
Ultimately, to live as a natural being.
最后活一个自然的人啊
To breathe with the earth.
与大地共呼吸
To share its fate.
共命运
Often, when we talk about it,
很多的时候来讲的话
If you follow the way of heaven,
如果你遵循天道啊
and the way of the earth.
遵循地道
Old Beijing is truly authentic.
老北京倍儿地道啊
If you follow the way of heaven and earth, the way of nature,
你要是遵循天地之道呢啊遵循这自然之道呢
In many aspects,
很多东西来讲
the advice in human society,
人类社会中的一些规劝
those norms and rituals,
哪一些礼教的东西啊
can make you feel particularly uncomfortable.
就显得特别难受了
Actually, the main core reason for your depression,
实际上造成你抑郁的主要的核心原因
is also the way they cultivate you as a talent,
也是这些把你当做人才的一种培养啊
I often say the education system treats us like scientists.
我常说教育系统是把咱们当中的科学家
Engineers are selected
工程师筛选出来
The main goal of modern education isn't to cultivate just anyone We talk about vocational education We need to provide targeted training We need to offer differentiated training In many cases Many people don't engage in research at universities
其他人啊其实不是现代教育培养的主要目的 咱们说要进行职业教育 要进行定向的培养 要进行分化培养 其实很多的时候来讲 很多人他不是在大学从事科研工作的时候
There's no need for them to attend high school
他没有必要去念高中啊
Many people mention vocational education in middle school
很多人说中学的职业教育
So, let's talk about it now.
所以现现现在来讲啊
You see, for the undergraduate program in directing,
你看啊本科啊这个导演系
and the acting program,
这个表演系
what we learn in these courses,
我我们学的这些东西来讲
is also part of the undergraduate curriculum.
它也是大学本科的内容
But I actually think the content of the acting program
但其实我认为表演系的内容
should be taught in high school,
起码应该高中就学习啊
when people are young and full of energy,
高中那时候人青春奔放
and their hormones are really surging.
荷尔蒙非常迸发的时候
She looks great
人长得也好看
and is full of energy
精力也旺盛
probably during junior and senior high school
应该是在中学初高中阶段
if you aspire to be a dance student
如果你有志于成为舞蹈生
a vocal student
成为声乐声
an art student
成为艺术生
or a performance student
表演生啊
how about we
咱怎么着
I am a media voice
我是媒体声
You should cultivate vocational education during high school.
你应该在高中的时候进行职业教育培养
Then, directly attend a junior college in the university stage.
在大学的阶段就直接就上大专
That's it after attending a higher vocational school.
上高职就完了
We talk about
咱们那贼
We also mention that those art schools have higher vocational accompaniment junior college classes.
咱们也说那些艺术院校都有高职伴奏大专班
But let's be honest here,
但是咱们说实在的啊
It's crucial to provide general scientific literacy education. We believe humans should possess basic scientific literacy, in this regard. It pertains to the core of modern civilization. This is a key factor in understanding it.
进行普遍的科学素质的教育是非常有必要的 咱们说人类具备有具有基本的科学素养的 来讲的话 是对现代文明啊 这个东西产生理解的一个核心的这个这个因素
Of course, if you have the capacity to learn further.
当然说在你学有余力的情况下
If studying isn't too strenuous for you.
唉学习不是特别费劲的话啊
You can complete high school.
能念高中啊
You can go on to a regular undergraduate program.
能正常念大学本科
It would actually be beneficial for you.
其实来讲对你来讲还是有帮助
Of course, for many professions.
当然来讲我们说很多职业来讲
He mentions cooking.
他就说炒菜
I should have started learning in junior high school.
我最好初中就学
Right?
对不对
When it comes to many things,
很多东西来讲的话
wasting time in high school, college, and graduate school,
浪费那个大学的高中的加大学加研究生的时间
it might not be as beneficial for your career development,
可能对你职业培养来讲的话
there might not be as many benefits.
可能是没有那么多的好处啊
That's why I always advise people to make the most of their resources,
所以我一直建议人要尽其财物
to use them to their fullest extent.
要尽其用
Think about what direction you want to develop in.
你想往自己往什么方向培养
Does the education system really help you?
教育系统到底对你有没有帮助
Does preparing for civil service exams or postgraduate studies really provide positive guidance?
考公考研对你到底有没有个正向的引导啊
So, you must think carefully about what modern education is.
所以你一定要考虑清楚现代教育是什么
You also need to consider this clearly.
你也要考虑清楚
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
If someone is becoming increasingly depressed,
我们说人如果要是活的越来越抑郁了
Is it because you're putting too much pressure on yourself?
你想是不是自己给自己加了码
There's more and more self-imposed social conditioning.
更多了自己对自己的社会化的规训的这种东西
It's becoming more and more prevalent.
越来越多了
Life has no referees. You decide how you should live. You determine your own path. Parental wishes. Matchmaker's words. I'll dedicate an episode to it in a couple of days. Criticizing the Disciple's Rules.
而人生是没有裁判的 你认为你该怎么样 甚为该你怎么样 父母之命 媒妁之言 我过两天会专门出一期 批判弟子规的这个这个东西
I am against Confucianism.
我是反儒家的
However, I don't deny the historical contributions of Confucius.
但是呢我不否定孔子这个人在历史上的功绩啊
But I hate how some people in later generations exploit Confucianism
但是我讨厌一些人后世利用这个儒家这些东西
exploit these ideas
利用这些思想
use these unnatural things to
利用这些不自然的啊东西来讲的话去
but what they call educating the people
但所谓的教化人民啊
how do I put it
对于这种怎么说呢
I think it's more of a harm to the people
更多来讲我认为这是一种对人民的一种伤害啊
but I believe in ancient philosophy
但是我认为古代的哲学里边
I'm not saying we should tear everything down
我不是说什么全推倒了
deny everything
什么全都不认啊
Even the ancestors of China wouldn't recognize it
是中国老祖宗都不认
But I do recognize the patriarch of Taoism
那道家老祖宗我是认得呀
Right?
对不对
So, when it comes to Taoist philosophy
所以道家的哲学来讲
Regarding how people should conduct themselves in life
对于人修身处世啊
What more can be said?
还怎么说呢
When considering more aspects
更多的东西来讲
You need to follow the laws of nature
你要遵循自然规律
What exactly are the laws of nature?
那自然规律是什么呢
It's physics
就是物理
Right?
对不对
So, as a high school science student
所以作为一个高中理科生
and then a college engineering student
大学又是工科生来讲啊
but my major was engineering
但我第一专业是工科
so I'd like to share with everyone
所以跟大家说
I mean, like the one we're about to build the nuclear fusion power plant in Jiangxi if you don't have a general scientific literacy You don't know what quantum mechanics is, right?
就是说就像咱们现在马上要建这个 在江西建这个核聚变的发电厂啊 如果你不具备有普遍的科学素养的话 量子力学你不知道是什么对吧
And you also don't know what nuclear fusion reactions are, do you?
呃核聚变反应你也不知道是什么
You don't understand physics and chemistry,
你不懂物理化学
especially nuclear fusion reactions,
不懂核聚变反应
right?
对不对
You can't even talk about things like electricity if you don't understand them.
不懂电学这些东西你都无从谈起啊
So when it comes to many things,
所以很多东西来讲
I think having a certain level of scientific literacy is necessary.
我觉得具有一定的基础科学素养是有必要的啊
Especially at this stage,
特别是我觉得这个阶段来讲的话
In junior high school, physics covered electricity.
那初中的啊物理就讲了电学啊
It also covered mechanics.
就讲了力学
I think this is really great.
我觉得这个东西是非常好的
When you're in junior high school,
你在初中啊
you learn physics, chemistry, biology, history, geography, and politics.
这个是物化生史地政都学这个东西
Looking back now,
是我觉得还是现在回过头来看
it's still very necessary.
还是非常有必要的
But there's one more thing to say,
但是我们还要说一句话呢
which is that everyone should use their resources to the fullest.
就是说人尽其财
Make the best use of everything
物尽其用
Those who start early should start even earlier
做的早的进行再早一些
How to put it, in terms of human
进行人类的这种怎么说呢
The differentiation in the cultivation of specialties
特长的培养方面的分化呢
It's actually a form of protection for talent
其实是对人才是一种保护
We won't beat around the bush
更多的呢咱们也不废话了啊
What we mainly want to do is
咱们主要就是想啊
There are many times in life
人生当中很多的时候
Obstacles that can't be avoided We might have to take some detours but there are ways to avoid certain pitfalls so we should try to steer clear of the traps we've discussed actually, in life, it's like this
没有办法避免的一些障碍呢 咱们可能要走一些冤枉路 但是有办法能避免的一些东西呢 就是咱们就尽量去避免咱们所说的避坑呢 其实人生当中他有这个怎么说呢
the chasm of faith
信仰的沟壑
the vast ocean of knowledge
知识的这个海洋
in a moment
在一瞬间当中呢
you might fall into a very deep abyss
你可能会跌入一个非常大的一个深渊里边
and be unable to climb out
爬不出来
But all these things between lives
但是人生之间的所有这些东西
If you base it on Wang Yangming's teachings
如果你根据王阳明的东西来讲
You'll understand the principles of Mind Learning
你就知道心学心机理
Many things are illusions created by the mind
很多东西是心创造的幻想啊
Not actual physical realities
不是实际存在的物理事实啊
That is to say, our minds
也就是说我们的心啊
Some of our aspects
我们的一些东西
Some of our aspirations
我们的一些发愿
Some of our shifts in thought
我们的一些一念之转呢
Sometimes he can alter your physical reality.
有的时候他会改变你的物理
Things in the real world.
现实中的东西
You'll change how you feel.
你会改改变你的感受啊
Often, when we talk about our feelings,
很多时候说我们的感受
Our emotional state,
我们的情绪价值
These aspects of ourselves,
我们的这些东西
The mental anguish we endure in reality,
我们现实当中受的这种精神折磨
Including the dreams you have,
包括你做的梦
Including your subconscious.
包括你的潜意识
Including your daily perceptions
包括你日常的这种认知
Actually, they have a more direct impact on you
其实他对你有更直接的影响
So we say that in life
所以我们说人生在世呢
The key is to get your underlying operating system right What is the purpose of your underlying operating system What are you fighting for What is the driving force that keeps you going every day The driving force that keeps me going every day Up to today
关键是要把自己的底层操作系统给弄好啊 底层的操作系统为什么而活 为什么而战啊 为什么是你每天活下去的动力啊 我每天活下的动力 我到今天啊
If we're talking about the basics
如果说我的基础的啊
the deep-seated belief, what is it really?
深层次的这个信仰到底是什么
This is my ultimate belief
这是我的最高信仰啊
Let's be honest
咱们说实在的
whether you study mysticism
你研究玄学也好啊
or various value systems
你研究各种各样的价值观也好
or Machiavelli
你研究马基亚维利也哈
these all fall into the realm of philosophy
这些都是哲学范畴的东西啊
the foundational thinking in political science
所谓治政治学的这种基础的思维的一种东西啊
As a means and strategy used in games
作为一种博弈当中的使用的手段和策略
it falls under strategy
算是属于strategy啊
and this belief
跟这个belief啊
how should I put it
跟这个怎么说
it's different from the line code
跟这个线条code它是不一样的
so when we talk about these things
所以这些东西来讲
we're referring to our basic coding methods, right
咱们说咱们的基础刻法是吧
the original code
original code啊
these underlying source codes
咱们这些底层源代码
What's our underlying code?
咱的底层代码是什么呢
Our underlying code, in simple terms, is to Serve the People.
咱底层代码说白了就是为人民服务啊
To give back to society.
回报这个社会啊
It's very much about humanistic care. Many people didn't believe it when they were young. But after growing up and comparing China and the U.S., they quickly understand that many things are realized through comparison. We are not perfect.
非常的具有人文关怀啊 很多人小时候不信 长大了以后进行中美一对仗啊 马上就明白了很多东西就是在相比之下得来的 我们不是完美的
We never claim to be perfect.
我们从来也不会自称完美
But if you are part of certain vulnerable groups in society
但是你如果是这个社会当中的啊某些弱势群体
For example, speaking of myself
比如说你看我自己啊
I have people with disabilities around me
我自己来讲身边有残疾人啊
And the disabled people around me have received particularly good care
我身边的残疾人都得到了特别啊良好的照顾啊
Moreover, quite often
而且很多的时候来讲呢
The social workers in our country
我们国家的这个这个社会的工作者呀
As well as these rescue organizations in society
还有这些社会的这些怎么救助团体
And those involved in the government
还有这些政治政府当中参与这些
Such as the China Disabled Persons' Federation and others, do a very thorough job
比如说残联啊之类的人的工作是很到位的
It's quite considerate
是很贴心的
person
人
among them
当中
without being like some of those
没有说像那些某些啊
certain Fascist types in the West
西方的某些法西斯主义的那种
claiming they are not
说他不自己不称
they don't think they are Fascist
他不觉得自己法西斯
but in reality, they are very, how should I put it
但实际上他们是非常的怎么说呢
inhumane
啊不不人道啊
It's really hard to put into words
非常的怎么说呢
It's Social Darwinism
就是社会达尔文主义啊
It's the law of the jungle
就是弱肉强食啊
Survival of the fittest
弱肉强食
Perhaps it is a real rule in many aspects of society But precisely because of the existence of such rules We need to do more to protect the weak To safeguard the interests of vulnerable groups For example, people are valuable because they are useful
也许是在社会上很多地方的真实的法则 但是正是因为这种法则的存在 我们才需要更多的去保护弱者 保护弱势群体更多的东西 比如说你说那人啊都是有价值才有用啊
It's all about Utilitarianism
都是功利主义
Then what about left-behind children?
那留守儿童算什么
And what about the elderly who live alone?
那孤寡老人算什么啊
They are all deemed useless to society.
都对社会没用了啊
Then what is to be done?
那怎么办
Right?
是不是
So in many cases,
所以很多的时候
People don't talk about things in life
人不是说在人生当中的东西
As if only the strong always prevail.
永远都是强的东西啊
It's always the utilitarian things that dominate.
永远都是功利的东西占主导的
If you are someone who is primarily guided by utilitarianism,
如果你是一个功利主义占主导人来讲
that is to say, if you don't apply Machiavellianism as a philosophy of struggle,
也就是说如果你拿马加雷马亚维利主义不做
but instead as a philosophy of life,
用作一个斗争的哲学
then you would be making a huge mistake.
而作为生活的哲学
In life, it's still better to align more with Wang Yangming,
那就大错特错了
and keep the idea of serving the people close to your heart.
生活上还是要贴近王阳明一些啊
Often, we talk about the three treasures and one struggle.
还是要把为民人民服务这个东西要挂在心头啊
Let's talk about the three treasures and one fight.
很多的时候来我们讲讲你三宝一斗啊
Two treasures in conflict
俩宝一斗
No matter what
不管怎么样
How many meals can you eat in a day?
你一天能吃几顿饭
In your extravagant lifestyle
你这穷奢极欲的情况下
You can't eat 15 eggs a day
你一天吃15个鸡蛋啊
Human indulgence
人的享受
These human desires
人的这些东西
Gradually, they all have their limits
慢慢它都是有极限的
Like me, my body is gradually not up to it What's the point of adding Xiao Mei to Little Sister? Your body just can't keep up, can it? Right? People have their natural laws. We age when it's time to age. A new generation is growing up. So how should you put it?
你像我慢慢的身体不行啊 你光小妹妹加微微有什么用啊 身体自己不行啊 对不对 人他有自然规律 该衰老就衰老 新的一代都长起来了 所以该你怎么说呢
You need to follow the laws of nature.
就是你要遵循自然的规律
So, fundamentally, we have this greater purpose to consider.
所以实在的我们还有这个大义的存在
What is the essence of righteousness?
大义的存在是什么呢
To protect the Earth's environment
保护地球环境
To genuinely love our home
真实的热爱我们的家园
Our nature is crucial
我们的大自然这个东西是很重要的
So there are many things we can do in life
所以人生在世有很多事情可以干啊
There are many things we can do
有很多事情可以干
So I talk to our gloomy ones
所以我就跟我们的郁闷的这些
I tell these gloomy friends
这些郁闷的小伙伴们说啊
Encouraging you to integrate into society is also a method
对你进行社会化的规劝他这也是一种手段
But ultimately, you are the one who shapes yourself.
但是你自己最终是形成塑造自己的主人翁
Not your parents,
而不是你的家长
not society,
而不是这个社会
but you yourself.
是你自己
What cause you dedicate your life to,
你在这一生当中投身于什么样的事业啊
what beliefs you hold dear,
投身于什么样的这种信仰当中
these are decisions you make.
这是你自己决定的
So, when it comes to you,
所以来讲在你当中
in your youth,
在你年轻当中
When you were in your teens
在你十几岁时候
In your twenties
20多岁
In your thirties
30多岁
And in your forties
40多岁的时候
I can assure you, your perspectives will change Your life goals will also evolve You won’t keep walking down the same path forever So, take a look at this comprehensive life guide And explore the various paths available I'm not saying everyone has to learn What's there for me to learn?
你的想法相信我一定会改变的 人生目标也会有改变 不会永远朝着一条道路走到黑啊 所以看看这本人生大攻略 看看各条道路上啊 我不是说大家一定要学 我学我有什么可学的呢
Right?
啊对不对
What's there to learn from me?
学我那么了
Middle-aged and divorced
中年离异
Taking care of a kid and two cats, right?
带个娃养两只猫是吗是吧
A man with a kid and cats
有娃带猫男
It's not like that
不是这样的啊
A man with a kid and a love for cats
有娃爱猫男
Not really.
不是的
No one can follow my exact path.
大家不可能完完全全跟我走一样的道路
But everyone’s journey is truly fascinating.
但是每个人的道路呢是很奇妙的
A small change,
其实改变一点
and you alter everything that follows.
你就改变了后来的一切的东西
But all roads lead to the same destination.
但是殊途同归
In my view,
我觉得来讲的话
the most crucial thing in life is to live with passion.
人生在世最重要的是活得痛快
To live happily.
活得开心啊
No matter what
无论怎么样
you need to remember
你要记住
you will definitely achieve your goal
你一定会达到你的目的
but what happens after you achieve it
但达到目的之后呢
it might just be empty and boring
可能就是空虚又无聊啊
anyway, I’ve fulfilled all my youthful dreams
反正我现在是实现了年轻时候所有的梦想
they’re all realized now
现在都实现了
a bit boring
有点无聊啊
a bit empty
有点空虚
So, life is about defining it yourself.
所以要人生在于自己自定义
It's about finding your own value and purpose.
找到自己存在的价值和意义就可以了
When you're young, one day,
等到有一天你在年轻的时候
you'll finally find
有一天你终于找到了
the value and meaning of your existence.
你存在的价值跟意义的时候
At that moment, you'll experience a supreme joy,
这个时候你会有一种无上的快乐
an incredible happiness. In life, I think, even though I also dream of being surrounded by beautiful people, I also want to live in a big house drive a big truck right? and then have 20 or 30 million followers, right?
特别喜乐啊 人生当中 我觉得啊虽然啊我也想美女成群啊 也想住大房子 开大货车 是不是 然后呢有个2000万3000万粉丝对吧
wouldn't that be great?
那就多好啊
right?
是不是
but the luxury and excess in life
但是人生的这个穷奢极欲啊
human desires do have limits
人的欲望是有极限的
the more you take from society
你在这个社会中你汲取的越多
The less others get
别人拿到的越少啊
So in many cases
所以说很多的时候来讲
If you can dedicate 10% of your life
如果你能够拿人生当中的10%的时
time and energy
间跟精力
to think about the elderly without family
想一想这社会上还有孤寡老人啊
think about disabled veterans
想一想还有什么残疾的复转军人
think about the left-behind children
想一想这社会上还有很多的留守儿童啊
Well
怎么说呢
many people need care in welfare homes
很多人啊需要在福利院
children in welfare homes
福利院里边的孩子
orphans, and such
孤儿之类的
if you can spend 10% of your time
你如果能有10%的时间啊
10% of your energy
10%的精力啊
you don’t need more, just think
不需要多了就议程啊
you should think about them
你要去想一想
just having them in your heart is enough
他们心中有一有他们就行了啊
it’s enough
就可以了
you would already be considered
你就已经算是一个
a very noble and good person
非常非常脱离了低级趣味的一个好人啊
Of course, in your daily life, there’s competition
当然来讲你日常当中啊博弈啊
and conflict, and you need to compete use it or lose it, right? isn’t that so? these things like natural selection do exist I’m not I’m not denying the existence of competition in life that’s why I wrote this book
战争经还要就跟人要竞争啊 这个这个用进废退 对不对啊 这个物物竞天择这些东西都是存在的 没有 我没有否认他人生当中有这个竞争性的存在 所以才写这本书啊
to help you
啊帮助你
if you can, how to say, advance and seek fame, and if you retreat
如果呢进呢能够怎么说呢
we can still be at peace with ourselves
求取功名退呢
there are things in life that can’t be balanced
咱们也能够啊无愧于心就可以了啊
not everything is
人生当中有些东西不是那么一碗水能端平的
a path to success
也不是说处处都是啊
there’s no science of success
通向成功
what is success?
人生没有成功学
it’s all about your own definition
什么是成功
so in life, there’s only a science of failure
都是在于自己定义
what is the science of failure?
所以呢人生呢只有失败学
it’s about not losing your high aspirations when you fail
失败学是什么
rising from the fields in the morning
就是在失败的时候
and entering the imperial court by night
在无论怎么样的哈
what is this called?
这叫什么呢
not losing your lofty ambitions
不坠青云之志啊
rising from the humblest beginnings
朝为天舍
brightly
朗
ascending to the imperial hall
暮登天子堂
in many cases
很多的时候来讲的话
you should think about what you should do
一定是想一想自己到底应该应该怎么办啊
when you’re lost
在你迷茫的时候
when your parents may not have
在你的父母可能没有那么的啊
the foresight and wisdom
具有远见卓识的时候呢
and they might have a negative impact on you
对你有一种负面的影响的时候呢
read this book by Brother Rong
看看荣哥这本书啊
this book might just make your life a bit smoother
这本书呢可能也就是能让你拉屎更顺畅一点啊
make your life a bit happier
能让你的人生更快乐一些啊
it’s not expensive
它也不贵啊
the cost of a KFC meal today, with VIVO50 you can get it in your hands I’ll see you on the 19th bye
一顿肯德基的钱 今天你VIVO50 你就能买到手啊 19号跟大家见面了啊 拜拜